My name is Akil.
名前はアキル
When I was 18,
my family moved to a new city.
18の時 家族で引っ越した
It was bad enough
leaving my friends behind.
友達と別れるのは辛かった
But now,
それに 新しくできるかも分からない
I wasn’t sure
if I could make new ones.
My parents seemed really happy.
両親はとても幸せそう
だから心配をかけたくない
I didn’t want
to make them feel bad
僕の気持ちを話すと
がっかりするだろうから
by telling them how I really felt.
The new school
wasn’t much better
学校は退屈だった
until I met Cameron.
キャメロンに会うまでは
He seemed
like a pretty cool guy.
いい奴そうだな
Soon, his friends
became my friends.
すぐに 友達が増えた
. . . something that David
believed was true,
…ダビデの信頼は心からのもので—
he actually proved it
by the association that he kept.
彼が保った友情がそれを証ししています
We think about one
of the closest friendships
ダビデとヨナタンの友情関係について—
recorded in the Scriptures,
聖書から考えてみましょう
and it was
that of David and Jonathan.
What was it that David and Jonathan
shared in common?
2人の友情は何に基づいていましたか？
年齢でしょうか？
It wasn’t their age.
アキル 集会中メールしてたわね
Akil,
you were texting in the meeting.
I shouldn’t have sent the text.
分かってる ごめん
I’m sorry.
But Cameron is a good person.
でも キャメロンはいい奴なんだ
He might even study one day.
いつか研究するかも
I understand that, Akil.
気持ちは分かるよ
But we all have to be careful
with how much time
でも エホバを愛さない人と
いつも一緒にいることには注意しないと
we spend with people
that don’t love Jehovah.
See,
their values are just different.
持ってる基準が違うね
You know
what Proverbs 13:20 says:
箴言 13章20節が言うように
“賢い者たちと共に歩”むんだ
‘Walk with those who are wise.’
So why don’t you seek out
friends who love Jehovah?
エホバを愛する友達を探してごらん
And you will make friends
that last a lifetime.
ずっと続く友達が見つかるよ
How am I supposed to do that?
どうやってできるの？
会衆に同い年なんていないよ
There’s no one my age
in the congregation.
親友は思いがけないところにいるものよ
Akil, good friends
can come from unexpected places.
Mom,
I had good friends
親友は…いたよ
—back home.
前にね
We all felt bad that night.
その夜はたくさん話し合った
The next day,
次の日 キャメロンが
パーティーの写真を見せてくれた
Cameron posted pictures
of a party he had.
My parents were right.
両親は正しかった
I broke off my association
with Cameron
キャメロン達と付き合うのはやめた
and his friends,
but I still felt
でも また独りぼっちだ
lost.
Hi, Akil?
アキル
土曜日だれかと奉仕する？
Do you have
field service plans for Saturday?
Ah, no.
ああ いえ
そう なら9時半に集合場所で
いいかい？
Good.
Now you do.
I’ll see you
at the 9:30 a.m. meeting, OK?
After service,
奉仕の後
マックス兄弟が家に招いてくれた
Max had the group
over for refreshments.
Did you take these?
兄弟これ……？
Do you like them?
気に入った？
Yeah.
ええ
My wife,
she was always the photographer.
妻が いつもカメラ持って—
She loved photography.
熱中していたんだ
And then one anniversary
she went out and bought me a camera,
で 結婚記念日に カメラをくれたんだ
and from that moment on,
I was hooked too.
それから わたしもとりこだよ
Time flies so quickly.
ほんとに早い
It’s hard to believe
she passed away 12 years ago now.
妻が亡くなってもう
12年も過ぎたとはね
I’m sorry.
そうですね
It’s OK.
まあね
But you still take pictures?
でも…今でも写真を？
I do.
I really enjoy photography.
ああ
撮るのは楽しいよ
There’s something about being close
特に相手は エホバの創造物だ
to Jehovah’s creation.
It reminds me
そんな時—
独りぼっちじゃないって感じるんだ
that we’re never really alone,
you know?
どう？
Good friends can come
from unexpected places
親友は思いがけないところにいる
年が違っても
and unexpected ages.
As I spent more time with Max,
兄弟と知り合うにつれて 分かったんだ
I realized it was
just like David and Jonathan.
ダビデとヨナタンみたいだ
2人の友情の基盤は—
Their friendship was based,
年齢じゃなく エホバへの愛だった
not on age,
but on their love for Jehovah.
そしてお互いに支え合った
And they helped each other.
マックス兄弟の助けで—
And with Max’s help,
今も良い霊的な習慣を
続けることができている
I was able to keep
a good spiritual routine
without interruption.
Although we weren’t the same age,
年が違っても 兄弟と親友になれた
Max became my good friend.
目を向ければよかったんだ
I just needed to see
what was right
目の前にある正しいことに
in front of me.